Amy X. Lu http://amyxlu.github.io github.com/amyxlu

amyxlu@cs.toronto.edu +1-647-968-6833 linkedin.com/in/amyxlu

Summary

I am a graduate student at the Vector Institute for AI, applying **computer vision and natural language processing algorithms to biological sequence data**, with an emphasis on **self-supervised representation learning, robustness, and biological interpretability**. I also serve on SVAI, which organizes research collaborations of genomics/AI researchers and industry partners for understudied rare disease patients.

EDUCATION

University of Waterloo

Waterloo, Canada

Bachelors of Science, Honours Science, Bioinformatics Option

2014 - 2019

University of Toronto, Vector Institute

Masters. Computer Science

Toronto, Canada 2019 - Present

EXPERIENCE

Stanford University

Palo Alto, USA

Visiting Student Researcher — Domain Adaptation in Regulatory Genomics, Dr. Anshul Kundaje

2019 - Present

• Domain adaptation, ChIP-seq analyses: Using domain adaptation to improve classifier performance and learned genomic sequence features for transcription factor binding when evaluating in a different cellular context.

University of Toronto/Vector Institute

Toronto, Canada

Masters Student — Representation learning in genomics, Dr. Alan Moses & Dr. Marzyeh Ghassemi 2019 – Present

- Natural language processing, self-supervised learning: Applying contextual word embedding models to learn robust and interpretable representations for genomic and proteomic sequences.
- \circ Algorithmic fairness: Quantitative and quaitative evaluation of bias in "black box" contextual clinical word embeddings, and attempting to debias using adversarial gradient-reversal. (Submitted to FAT* 2020)
- Generalizability, computer vision: Benchmarked a new "paired cell in-painting" method for out-of-sample generalization in microscopy against various common computer vision algorithms. (NeurIPS 2019; ICML 2019 Self-Supervised Learning Workshop)

Harvard Medical School/Boston Children's Hospital

Boston, USA

Research Intern — Deep Learning in Clinical Genomics, Sliz Lab

2018 - Present

- Variant analysis, genotype-phenotype studies: Applying standard filtering pipelines to a whole exome (WES) dataset of epilepsy patients
- Machine learning, dimensionality reduction: Building machine learning models to classify disease phenotype from high-dimensional exome variant data

University of Waterloo

Waterloo, Canada

 $Undergraduate\ Thesis\ Student-Deep\ Learning\ in\ Regulatory\ Genomics,\ Doxey\ Lab$

2017 - 2018

- Convolutional neural networks in genomics: Implemented a convolutional neural network which recognizes genomic enhancers regulating femur growth with 91% accuracy.
- Interpretability: Distilled biological knowledge from the "black box" network by reconstructing first-layer features as position-weighted matrices (PWMs) of "motifs" (i.e. genomic patterns). All motifs found statistical matches in JASPAR (an experimentally-verified motifs database).
- Self-directed learning: Self-learned deep learning concepts and Python as a biology student.

École polytechnique fédérale de Lausanne

Lausanne, Switzerland

Research Intern — Computational Biology, Laboratory for Biomolecular Modelling

2017

- Molecular dynamics: Contributed three potential findings on enzyme-membrane mechanisms of bacterial "superbugs" using computational simulations based on molecular dynamics (MD) principles.
- Automating workflows: Increased workflow efficiency by writing R, tcl/tk, and Csh scripts.

University of Toronto

Toronto, Canada

Research Intern — Data Visualization in Pharmacoepidemiology, Cadarette Lab

2015 - 2017

- **Pharmacoepidemiology:** Took initiative to redesign manual workflows. Contributed two co-authored publications, one poster, and figures for an international epidemiology conference within two months.
- Data visualization: Wrangled data using R and SQL to create animated and interactive co-authorship networks.

SERVICE AND ACTIVITIES

- **SVAI:** Core Team of SVAI, a non-profit connecting patients of rare genomic diseases to the medical/AI research community and industry partners through collaborative research initiatives.
- Residence Don, Velocity Incubator: Leader for the residence program of Canada's most productive start-up incubator; fostered close relations with diverse students to support conduct and mental health crises
- Tosamaganga Hospital, Tanzania: Supported operations at a rural Tanzanian hospital and shadowed surgical procedures. Expenses were covered by scholarships, fundraising, and part-time tutoring.
- Teaching Assistant: Taught weekly tutorial lectures for a 200-level genetics course.

AWARDS

- NSERC Michael Smith Foreign Supplement: Supports high-calibre Canadian graduate students in pursuing research abroad. Valued at \$6,000.
- Canada Graduate Scholarships-Master's (CGS-M) Award: NSERC federal research grant. Valued at \$17,500.
- Scholarship of Excellence in Research: One of 13 students sponsored for research at EPFL. Valued at CHF 4500.
- University of Waterloo: Various entrance awards totaling \$6000.
- Associate of The Royal Conservatory (ARCT): Performer's Diploma in Piano (highest academic standing offered).

Publications and Conference Proceedings

- Accepted: Lu AX, Lu AXP, Moses A. The Cells Out of Sample (COOS) dataset and benchmarks for measuring out-of-sample generalization of image classifiers. *NeurIPS 2019*.
- Published: Ban J, Tadrous M, Lu AX, Cicinelli EA, Cadarette SM. Diffusion of indirect comparison meta-analytic methods to study drugs: a systematic review and co-authorship network analysis. *BMJ Open.*
- Under revision: Consiglio GP, Maclure M, Lu AX, Cicinelli EA, Ban JK, McCarthy L, Cadarette SM. Guidance documents for the application of Self-controlled Crossover Observational PharmacoEpidemiology (SCOPE) designs are needed: systematic review and animated co-authorship networks. Submitted to Pharmacoepi Drug Saf.

Workshop Papers

• Lu AX, Lu AXP, Moses A. Paired Cell Inpainting: A Multiple-Instance Extension of Self-Supervised Learning for Bioimage Analysis. *ICML 2019 Workshop on Self-Supervised Learning*.

Posters

- Presented: Lu AX, Rockowitz S, Poduri A, Sliz P. From data to precision medicine: predictive machine learning models to uncover disease-associated variants. Poster presentation, November 2019. *Harvard Medical School BCMP Retreat 2019*.
- Presented: Lu AX, Consiglio GP, Cadarette SM. Dynamic Visualization in Co-Authorship Network Analysis. Poster presentation, August 2016. Leslie Dan Faculty of Pharmacy Undergraduate Research Symposium.
- Presented: McIlroy-Young R, Lu AX, Guenther N, Olarnyk A. A Network Analysis: Did the Arab Spring Impact the Academic Network of Tunisia Between 2010 and 2015? Poster presentation, April 2015. *Knowledge Integration Symposium*.
- Submitted: Lu AX, Tam ES. Effect of prophylactic brimonidine on subconjunctival hemorrhage in laser-assisted cataract surgery. Poster abstract. Submitted to American Academy of Ophthalmology 2017.

HACKATHONS AND PROJECTS

- NLP-seq: Used n-grams to extract features for supervised learning of function prediction, trained on Protein Data Bank data.
- Chatsense: Mobile chat app using a sentiment analysis machine learning API on voice messages and mapping dominant emotions to emojis, designed for the autistic community. *Team project. Winner at YHacks at Yale.*
- Alice: Web login page using a trained facial recognition model to login to online banking without passwords, designed for dementia patients. *Team project. Winner at ConUHacks III.*